There are situations when conflict already resolved
have to be resolved once again. For example
we start to rebase. Place some commits over commits.
Resolve conflicts from them. And here happens that we have to '--abort' the rebase.
Thus when we rebase again
the same conflicts will emerge.
Or if we've just merged but need to revert it.
To make some minor changes needed.
After which we try to merge it once again but end up with the same conflicts.
Or a more tricky example.
If we pull up and apply forward changes to branch by merges.
But those merges contained conflicts.
After which we decide to rebase the branch.
Then presumably you'll meet same conflicts.
You can find situations in development process. Where you have to resolve conflicts in repeat. That would be better if I would list them for you.
Alas, nobody likes to do same things twice.
Happily ever Git is able to do it automatically.
with the tool 'rerere'.
Shortened from REuse, REcorded, REsolution.
When you enable this tool. Git will remember how conflicts were resolved.
If the same conflicts arises again
they will be resolved automatically.
For example, let's take the repository we worked before
and foremost switch on to the 'rerere' tool.
git config 'rerere.enabled true'
Now let's merge to master branch.
We see a conflict. I'd like to draw your attention to the conflict message
which appears only If 'rerere' is working. And means
'rerere' tool remembered index.html current state
before the conflicts are resolved.
Now, let's fix our conflict in editor.
This is how our index.html looks like.
We add changes: 'git add index.html' , and finish the merge: 'git commit --no-edit'. Ready.
Here we see one more message.
Which appears again only with help of 'rerere' enabled.
Is how Git remembers the conflict resolution.
For now let's imagine, that I've found out that something goes wrong.
And I merged too early.
Well, I have to cancel it.
And I will do it by going 1 commit backward:
'git reset --hard @~'
Next I can make some changes on 'feature' branch or 'master' branch
Or in both. From 'rerere's side
changes are unimportant only If it doesn't touch the conflict.
It means that if we would have in future same conflict
in same file. Then 'rerere' will work out.
But other changes does make no sense.
For clarity, I will run merge process once again: 'git merge master'
Looks like everything is the same. But here we see short message
from 'rerere' that tells us
that the conflict is resolved automatically using the result saved from previous conflict resolution, same type
And if we see the index.html inside
Indeed, there is no any conflict.
Means 'rerere' applies conflict resolution to a file which it remembers but didn't add it by default to index.html
Option you can easily add with
'git config rerere.autoupdate true'
a special configuration adjustment for 'rerere'
Then 'rerere' would not only be able to resolve the conflict but also index it
On the opposite it's probably better without
Because this way we can clearly see files with conflicts
And can manage that the conflict were resolved accurately
If so, add files to the index and finish the merge as intended
What if it's not. If previous stored conflict resolution
now is obsolete and doesn't fit our changes.
Then we can get the file with conflict by
'git checkout --merge index.html'
Call 'rerere' forget
'git rerere forget index.html'
to forget old conflict resolution
Without that command 'rerere' would not be able to remember new resolution we will make right now
and change it as we think it's needed
For example let's have those calls for now splitted.
This is how will index.html look like
Merge it once again. Finished.
Now we see an example of 'rerere'
with merge command
Usually Git has different commands for joining files together
'rerere' works for them automatically also.
Let's make rebase from 'feature' to 'master' branch
I'll recall that rebase skips the merge step
So, this 2 commits will be rebased over in 'master'
First commit as we see is rebased successfully
Rebasing the 2nd commit brings a conflict
He's totally the same as it was in previous merge
This are only same changes applied one over the other.
The difference is that on previous example joining was done by 'merge' command but now it's done by 'rebase'
But 'rerere' doesn't keep any difference between. The conflict is the same
that's why it resolves it easily
Let's open the file
To see that, yeah, the conflict is not there. Such conflict resolution is trusty
we just have to add it to the index.html
and finish the rebase.
Git stores all data on 'rerere' conflicts
in directory
There is nothing more in that directory
So, If we decide that we have to forget all conflict resolutions
We need just to delete the directory
Git deletes old conflict solutions
automatically during the garbage collection
If they are older than this config parameter...
60 days by default
Data of unresolved conflicts are deleted if they are older than this parameter
15 days by default
If 'rerere' bored you. And you want to switch it off.
And start to resolve conflicts by yourself again.
You can set config setting for this tool as 'false'
Or you can delete it
But be cautious that with deletion of this config parameter
you have to kill the directory specified for 'rerere'
Otherwise git will account that 'rerere' is working
'rerere' has it's own learning script
which goes through branches, analyse merge commits
and remembers previous conflict resolutions
including those conflicts that were resolved before the 'rerere' was turned on
This script is called 'rerere train'
Usually it's located inside the Git installation
in subdirectory 'contrib' not in the system PATH
In my case it's here. Your path may be different
It is supplied with commit from which it will start to analyze
or it is supplied with 'all' to go through all branches
I'll note that in this case this command does nothing
Because as we could see from right side image
we have no any merges after rebase
Virtually happens that conflict we are interested in
is located in unreachable commit
We could assign it clearly
In our case we just rebased from an old merge
That's why we can point to it through 'reflog'
Here we have outputs that shows us
that the tool is already taught
Respectively if we work with 'rerere' disabled
But we have to resolve same conflict once again
We can supply script with 'all' branches
Or if the commit is old commit resolution is too far to be reached
we can pass it in some other way
through 'id' or as I did through 'reflog'
Then 'rerere' will resolve alike conflicts automatically
As I previously said
on garbage collection 'rerere' deletes previous old conflict resolutions
by default which are older than 60 days from creation
but 'rerere train'
can read them again if needed commits still exist
means to restore
Finally I will mention that script 'rerere train'
is written in shell language (sh)
That's why on Windows it will work using Git bash
and not from PowerShell or cmd.